ANS Record Group 2: Curatorial, 1858-ongoing
ANS Archives
- Series 6: Curatorial loan records, 1918-2007, bulk 1980-2007; 6 cubic feet (7 boxes and 1 loose item)
  - Box 3 of 7: Outgoing Loans
    - National Gallery of Art, 1982
    - Smithsonian Institution, Analytical Lab, 1985
    - Snug Harbor Cultural Center, 1983
    - State University of New York at Binghamton – Crusades exhibit, 1980
    - University of Michigan – The Meeting of the Worlds, 1980-1981
    - University of Michigan, 1979-1980
    - University of Michigan, 1979-1980
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1977-1978
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1976-1977
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art – The Age of Spirituality, 1977-1978
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1975-1976
    - Museum of National Guard, 1975
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1974-1975
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1973-1974
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1972-1973
    - International Numismatic Congress – Indian Museum – Eric P. Newman, 1973
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1971-1972
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1970-1971
    - Loan journal – Dead file, 1969-1974
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1969-1970
    - Coins back at ANS - World’s Fair, 1962-1970
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1968-1969
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1967-1968
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1966-1967
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1965-1966
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1958-1965
    - Coins back at ANS – Barcelona, 1958-1959
    - Loans completed – Coins back at ANS, 1949-1957
  - Box 4 of 7: Outgoing loans (continued)
    - New York Public Library, 2003-2004
    - Hood Museum, Dartmouth College, Hanover, N.H. – traveling exhibit, 2002-2004
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art – Byzantine exhibit, 2004
    - Frick Collection, 2005
    - Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation Victory Center – Canceled, 2000-2001
    - Cornish Colony Museum, 2004
    - Swiss National Museum, 1990-1992
    - International Jewish Committee – Golden Threads – Canceled, 1992
    - Franklin Mint, 1976-1992
    - Memphis Brooks Museum of Art – Turkish Romance, 1992
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art – Al Andalus: The Art of Islamic Spain, 1991-1993
    - Museum of the Confederacy, 1990-1991
    - New York Numismatic Convention, 1992
    - Brunner Gallery and Museum, 1988
    - Grey Art Gallery and Study Center – New York University, 1991
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, Conservation Department, 1990-1991
    - Stolen coins – Post office theft – Replacement loan to Eastern Michigan University, 1990
    - Joseph Lasser, 1991
    - Eric Newman, 1990-1991
    - Onassis Center, 1990
    - Museum of our National Heritage, 1989
    - U.S. Mint – Canceled, 1991
    - Loans from ANS – Mint Museum – Museum of Art – Bechtler coin press, 1978-1990
    - National Portrait Gallery – Andrew Jackson medal, 1990
    - Museum of the City of New York, 1965-1991
    - Tercentenary of William and Mary, 1988
    - PNG – Cincinnati, 1988
    - Philadelphia Maritime Museum, 1985-1987
    - NYNC (New York Numismatic Club), 1988
    - National Portrait Gallery, 1986-1988
    - Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, 1985-1988
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art – Loans for conservation study, 1989
    - Kresge Art Museum, 1987
    - Loan to Peter Gaspar 1988-1989
    - Brown University – Bell Gallery, 1988-1989
    - Bowers and Merena, 1988
    - Bank of Canada, 1988-1989
    - Loomis Chaffee School, 1992-1993
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1993
    - ZPAP – Polish exhibit – Saltus award, 1993
    - Newark Museum, 1991-1993
    - Museum of the American Indian – Long-term loan since 1926 – Silver arm band, 1993
    - Corning Museum of Glass, 1980-1991
    - South Carolina’s State Museum – New Deal Art - Canceled, 1993
    - Loan from the ANS – John H. Kroll – University of Texas, 1985
    - (ANA) American Numismatic Association – FIDEM (Fédération Internationale de la Médaille), 1987
    - ANS material to (1) Society for the Study of Crusades, (2) American Numismatic Association, 1991
    - Manhattanville College – Loan not actualized, 1992
    - Meeting – Toronto – Hofstra University, 1997
    - Loan – University of Missouri – Kushan coins, 1982-1997
    - Palazzo Delle Esposizioni, 1994-1995
    - Bruce Smith – Harvard, 1993
    - Hofstra University Museum, 1994-1996
    - Mantua Loan, 1994-1995
    - Virginia Historical Society, 1992-1995
    - Intercultura, 1993-1995
    - Onasis Center, 1995
    - Yale University, 1996-1997
    - Jewish Museum loan, 1997
    - Frick exhibit, 1997
    - National Gallery – Frick exhibit, 1992-1993
    - Katonah – Medieval, 1995
    - Yeshiva University Museum, 1996-1997
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art – Loan of Greek gold, 1994
    - Yale Art Gallery – Tyche
    - Baltimore Museum of Art, 1994
    - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 1991-1993
    - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 1991-1993
    - Corning Museum of Glass, 1983, 1993
    - Hood Museum, Dartmouth College, 1992-1993
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art – The Glory of Byzantium, 1996-1997
  - Box 5 of 7: Outgoing loans (continued)
    - Hispanic Society of America objects on loan, 2007
    - Exhibits: Treasures of Ancient Coinage and others, labels, etc., 2000-2001
    - Byzantine exhibit labels
    - Chester County Historical Society, 2001-2003
    - New Orleans Museum, 2002-2003
    - Nassau County Museum, 2000-2003
    - Reed College, 2002
    - Bruce Museum of Arts and Sciences, 2001
    - Fraunces Tavern, 2000-2001
    - Baltimore Museum of Art, 2000-2001
    - Washington – Coin Designs Worthy of a Great Nation, 2000
    - The Field Museum, 2001-2002
    - Katonah Museum of Art, 2001
    - British Museum, 2000
    - Museum of Art and Archaeology – Kushan, 2000-2001
    - Worchester Art Museum, 2000
    - Winterthur Museum, 2000-2001
    - Yale, 1999-2000
    - Michael C. Carlos Museum – Maureen Morrisette, 2000
    - British Museum and Field Museum, 1999-2000
    - South Carolina State Museum, 1998
    - Montreal Museum, 1999
    - V. Fleischer Museum, 1999
    - Fraunces Tavern, 1999
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art – Egypt, 2000
    - University of Nottingham, 1999
    - Museums at Stony Point, 1998-2000
    - New Jersey Historical Society – Canfield collection, 1995-2004
    - Mount Holyoke, 1999
    - Order of Indian Wars, 1999
    - Mississippi River Museum, Memphis, 1999
    - ANA (American Numismatic Association) convention, 1998
    - Text for annual “New Acquisitions Exhibit” – Exhibit label samples
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1995
    - Fredericksburg Area Museum, 1995
    - Newseum – Todd Alan Kinser, 1996-2001
    - Michael Carlos Museum – Atlanta, 1995-1996
    - Saint-Gaudens loan, 1998
    - Fine Arts Museum of San Francisco, 1996
    - Hudson River Museum, 1995-1996
    - Museum of Natural History – Permanent loan from ANS, 1975-1996
    - Museum of the City of New York, 1996
    - Museum of Fine Arts, St. Petersburg, Florida – Georgia Museum of Art, Athens – Canceled, 1994-1996
    - Intrepid – Canceled, 1993
    - Yale University Art Gallery, 1999
    - Katonah Gallery, 1988
    - National Portrait Gallery – Indian peace medals – With photographs, 1984-1992
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1985-1986
    - Loans out of building, 1989-2002
    - University of Illinois – Paul Keyser – Microprobe analysis, 1990
    - Mariners Museum, 1997-2000
  - Box 6 of 7: Outgoing loans (continued)
    - Loans request for council meeting, 1999-2006
    - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 2003-2004
    - Spertus Museum, 2001
    - Bruce Museum, 2005-2006
    - Knights of Columbus Museum, 2007
    - Hispanic Society of America, Freer Gallery, 2003-2004
    - Missouri History Museum, 2001-2004
    - Onassis loan, 1998-2005
    - Onassis, 2006
    - Peabody Essex Museum, 2006
    - Princeton University Art Museum, 2004
    - Seton Hall University, 2005
    - Tampa Museum of Art, 1982-2006
    - Trust for Museum exhibition, 1998-2006
    - Virginia Historical Society, 1998-2004 (1 of 2)
    - Virginia Historical Society, 1998-2004 (2 of 2)
    - Wenham Museum, 2006
    - Yorktown, 1994-2006
  - Box 7 of 7: Incoming and Outgoing
    - Loans—Incoming, 1938-1949
    - Augustan Exhibition—Eight color plates
    - New-York Historical Society, 1918
    - Société Francaise de Numismatique—Buy back fund, 1964
    - Letters releasing ANS from responsibility for property loaned by institutions, etc., 1950-1955, 1969
    - Letters releasing ANS from responsibility for property stored in museum by individuals, 1950
    - Homer St. Gaudens—The return of two gold medals loaned to us by his mother, 1950
    - Metropolitan Museum (Coins)—Lists, 1926-1973
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art—Regarding possibility of permanent loan, 1937
    - Metropolitan Museum—Resolutions, clippings, etc., 1973
    - Completed Metropolitan Museum, 1981-1982
    - Completed Metropolitan Museum of Art—The Cloisters,1979-1981
    - Metropolitan Museum Correspondence—Coins, 1972-1973
    - #299—Sotheby and recalled Metropolitan coins, 1972-1973
    - Buy Back Fund--#299 Sotheby—Auction, 1973
  - Photograph Album
    Contains photographs of The Gwynne M. Andrews Collection loaned by the Metropolitan Museum of Art, February 16, 1931, and images of coins loaned in 1930, 1935, 1936.
- Series 7: Exhibition records, 1900-2010; 5.5 cubic feet (6 boxes and 1 loose item)
  Exposition universelle internationale de 1900 (Paris, France); Scudder, Janet, 1869-1940; Boyle, John J., 1851-1917; Fourcade, Dominique Philippe Jean; Correspondence; Photographs; Exhibition records; Exhibition catalogs; Exhibit scripts; Invitations; Brochures; Floor plans; Architectural drawings (Visual works); Logs (Records)
  For photographs from Exhibition of Early American Coinage (1942) see the Sydney Noe Papers in the ANS Archives.
  For additional materials relating to items loaned by and to the ANS for exhibits, see the Curatorial Loan Records series in this record group (RG2: Curatorial).
  Contains records relating to some of the exhibitions produced by the American Numismatic Society, most of which were held at the ANS headquarters building, though also included are files from the traveling exhibit program (1945-1970s) and a file on the Society’s exhibit at the Paris Exposition of 1900 that has correspondence, invoices, and insurance policy documents relating to the arrangements made for participating in the exhibition. The kinds and amounts of material available for each exhibit vary, with some represented by just an exhibition catalog or brochure and others having correspondence and photographs of pieces displayed. Several important early exhibits are represented, such as the International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals (1910), from which is a large scrapbook containing photographs documenting the pieces loaned for the exhibit, mostly pasted in but with some loose, and others mounted on board, as in the case of several photographs from Dominique Philippe Jean Fourcade and Janet Scudder. (Two sets of photographs, showing the obverse and reverse of medals by John J. Boyle for The Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts and The Art Club of Philadelphia seem to have been misfiled in the scrapbook). Additionally, there is a register book used for the 1910 exhibit to log loaned items, a separate loan book, and loan delivery cards. There also is a set of proof sheets of coin photographs from an exhibit of U.S. colonial coins (1914). Records relating to an exhibit commemorating the bi-millennium of the birth of Caesar Augustus (1938) includes correspondence regarding loans and invitations as well as photographs of exhibited items. Materials from the Exhibition of Early American Coinage (1942) contains correspondence having to do with promoting the exhibit and regarding the items loaned for display. (For photographs from the exhibit, see the Sydney Noe Papers in the ANS Archives.) Files from the Exhibition of the Coinages of the Ancient, Mediaeval, and Modern East (1948) contain exhibit label text and photographs. Two later exhibits are well documented: for The World of Coins (1983-2004), which occupied the Society’s Audubon headquarters West Hall during the two decades prior to its move downtown in 2004, there are plans, architectural drawings, outlines, scripts, and grant materials; for an exhibit celebrating the 100th anniversary of the New York Numismatic Club (2008) there are, among other things, loan forms with accompanying descriptions of the loaned items that were intended for use as exhibit text.
  - Box 1 of 7
    - Exhibitions – invitations and admission cards, early 20th c.?
    - Paris Exposition, 1900
    - Circular for the Catalogue of the International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals, 1911
    - Augustan (Augustus) exhibition, 1938 (1 of 2)
    - Augustan (Augustus) exhibition, 1938 (2 of 2)
    - Augustan (Augustus) exhibition – Clippings, 1938
    - Augustan exhibition photograph book, 1938
    - Exhibition of Early American Coinage, 1942
    - Exhibition of Early American Coinage – Brochures, 1942
    - Exhibition of Early American Coinage – A-M, 1942
    - Exhibition of Early American Coinage – N-Z, 1942
    - Spanish exhibition – Hans M.F. Schulman, 1951
    - Traveling exhibition, 1945-1966
    - Traveling exhibits – Assembly instructions, undated
    - Traveling exhibit – Request, 1979
    - Traveling exhibit – George Washington in Medallic Art – Brochures, 1970s
    - Traveling exhibit – Coinage of Judaea – Brochures, undated
    - Traveling exhibit – Chinese Communist Money – Brochures, 1979
    - Coin exhibit photographs (Coins of the Centuries?) – 500 B.C. to 1 B.C., undated
    - Exhibition of the Coinages of the Ancient, Mediaeval, and Modern East, 1948 (1 of 3)
    - Exhibition of the Coinages of the Ancient, Mediaeval, and Modern East, 1948 (2 of 3)
    - Exhibition of the Coinages of the Ancient, Mediaeval, and Modern East, 1948 (3 of 3)
    - Exhibit – Birds on Ancient Greek Coins – Photographs, 1972
    - Permanent exhibit photographic prints – Peace medals (?), John Paulding medal, Joan of Arc, circa 1950s-1980s
    - Exhibition? – Photographic prints of U.S. Mint buildings, 1980s?
    - Exhibit – An American in China, The L. Irvine Moffett Collection – Photographs, 1973
    - East and West Hall exhibit layout, 1953
    - Exhibition cases – Inventory and evaluation, 1964
    - Estimate of exhibition cases, 1964
    - Exhibits – Returned to vault, 1967
    - Harold Center exhibition space, 1983
    - Memoranda, correspondence, and photographs relating to exhibits and other issues, 1970-1986
    - Exhibit – Presidential campaign buttons, 1960s?
    - Exhibit – The Flight of Man, 1973
    - Exhibits – Charles Edison Fund, 1976
    - Exhibits – Brochures, undated
  - Box 2 of 7
    - FIDEM
    - American Medallic Sculpture Association exhibit catalogs, 1983-1984
    - Beaux arts medal - Book and exhibit, 1988
    - Exhibit - The Beaux-Arts Medal in America - Brochures, 1987-1988
    - The Beaux-Arts Medal in America
    - Exhibit - Indian Peace Medals - Brochure
    - Exhibit catalog – The Currency of Fame: Portrait Medals of the Renaissance, 1994 (two loose copies)
    - Exhibit catalog – Treasures of Ancient Coinage, 1996
    - Exhibit catalog – The Proud Republic: Dutch Medals of the Golden Age, 1997 (three loose copies)
    - Exhibit catalog – New Ideas in Medallic Sculpture – Saltus, 1998-1999
    - Exhibit – Drachmas, Dubloons, and Dollars – Brochures, circa 2001
    - Docent meeting materials – Federal Reserve, 2001
    - Exhibit script – Drachmas Doubloons, and Dollars – The History of Money, circa 2001
    - Byzantine Hoard – Israel Antiquities Authority – 2003
    - Byzantine Hoard, 2003
    - Exhibit – Full Circle: The Olympic Heritage in Coins and Medals – Brochure, 2003-2004
    - Olympics, 2003
    - Olympic exhibit, 2005 (1 of 4)
    - Olympic exhibit, 2005 (2 of 4)
    - Olympic exhibit, 2005 (3 of 4)
    - Olympic exhibit, 2005 (4 of 4)
    - Olympic – Bernth Ahlstrom, 2006
    - New York Steel exhibition, 2005 (1 of 2)
    - New York Steel exhibition, 2005 (2 of 2)
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Friends of, 2005
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Image requests, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Panels, cases, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Loeb & Barrera, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Announcement, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – List and labels, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition prep, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition catalog – Grant application, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Grant, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Insurance, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens newsletter, 2007
    - Saint-Gaudens exhibition – Brochures, magazine and newspaper articles, and DVD of film, 2007
    - Exhibit catalog – One Hundred Years of Solicitude: Collecting by the New York Numismatic Club, 2008 (two loose copies)
    - Exhibit – Funny Money – Scan of secret service notebook (1901-1902), 2010
  - Box 3 of 7 - World of Coins exhibit
    - Exhibit – World of Coins – Brochure, undated
    - New York State Council on the Arts (NYSCA) – World of Money, 1979
    - World of Coins, 1978-1979
    - Grants – Including exhibit, 1977
    - World of Coins – Grants and other preliminary, 1977
    - World of Coins – Prototype, 1978
    - World of Coins exhibition information, 1983-1996
    - World of Coins – Draft, undated
    - Exhibit text – Master copy
    - World of Coins exhibit outline, 1978 (1 of 2)
    - World of Coins exhibit outline, 1978 (2 of 2)
    - Secondary panels, undated
    - Polo
    - Before
    - Renaissance
    - Machinery
    - Dollar
    - Modern Economy
    - Money/Message
    - Denarius
    - Solidus/Byzantine
    - World of Coins - Architectural drawings of floor and exhibit plans
  - Box 4 of 7 - New York Numismatic Club centennial exhibit, 2008
    - NYNC item list
    - NYNC exhibit – Insurance
    - NYNC exhibit – Labels/Description
    - NYNC catalog
    - NYNC exhibit
    - NYNC centennial exhibit write ups
    - NYNC exhibit forms
    - NYNC exhibit layout
    - NYNC history/medals panel
    - Alexander, David – Loan forms
    - Cuhaj, George – Loan forms
    - Erlichman, Jay – Loan forms
    - Fleishmann, David – Loan forms
    - Galst, Jay – Loan forms
    - Haggerty, Jerry – Loan forms
    - Herzon, John – Loan forms
    - Hoge, Bob – Loan forms
    - Kagen, Jonathan – Loan forms
    - Knapp, Bob – Loan forms
    - Lande, David – Loan forms
    - Low, Darrell – Loan forms
    - Margolis, Richard – Loan forms
    - Marinescu, Constantin – Loan forms
    - Menchell, David – Loan forms
    - Miller, Scott – Loan forms
    - Parris, Michael – Loan forms
    - Rezak, Ira – Loan forms
    - Sacks, Bob – Loan forms
    - Schaaf, Robert – Loan forms
    - Scher, Steve – Loan forms
    - Siboni, Roger – Loan forms
    - Simpson, David – Loan forms
    - Terranova, Tony – Loan forms
    - Tesorlero, Tom – Loan forms
    - Tomasko, Mark – Loan forms
    - Van Alfen, Peter – Loan forms
    - Witschonke, Rick – Loan forms
  - Box 5 of 7 - Flat file and oversized
    - Spiral bound outline of the World of Coins exhibit (6 loose copies)
    - World of coins architectural drawings of exhibits and floor plans (loose)
    - Exhibit – U.S. colonial coins – Photographs, proof sheets for illustrations, 1914
    - Augustan exhibit – Photostats, 1938
    - World of Coins visitors log book, 1990-1995
    - Exhibit labels – Washington exhibit, undated
    - International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals loan book, 1910
    - International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals loan cards, 1910
  - Box 6 of 7 - International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals photograph album, 1910
  - 7 of 7 [loose] - International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals register log book, 1910
- Series 8: Envelopes from Bates and Heaton coin collections, 1984-1985; 1.5 cubic feet (2 boxes)
  Envelopes; Bates, George Eugene; Heaton, Charles T.
  Empty annotated coin envelopes from the George Eugene Bates Byzantine coin collection (1984.61) and the Charles T. Heaton coin club medals collection (1985.67)
  - Box 1 of 2: Bates
  - Box 2 of 2: Heaton
- Series 9: Howland Wood curator correspondence and other material, 1913-1937; 10 cubic feet (12 boxes)
  Mostly official correspondence from Howland Wood’s work as curator of the American Numismatic Society (ANS). Many of the letters are to and from dealers, ANS members, and the general public and involve matters such as the authentication and value of individual coins as well as coin donations, purchasing, items sent on approval, and other efforts to add to and document the ANS collections, including its holdings in Indian Peace Medals and medals relating to World War I. Occasionally, coin rubbings and photographs are included. Also discussed are building security issues, such as a theft of coins from the J.P. Morgan and D.O. Mills collections (Newell, 1927); employee matters, such as hiring an assistant curator upon the death of Robert Robertson in 1937 (e.g., Duffield, Jan. 27, 1937), and lists of employees and salaries (see Union Trust Company). Other topics include Wood’s work as editor of the American Journal of Numismatics, such as discussions of article content and production issues; photographing and casting of coins; cleaning of coins (e.g., Hopkins, March 4, 1931 and Oliveira, May 16, 1933); exhibits; the return of the Andrew Zabriskie collection, with a catalog of Polish coins returned (1924); the addition to the building at Audubon Terrace (see Eidlitz, 1921-1934); the Bechtler coin press donated to the ANS (Tapp, 1926-1928); the loan of the Frederick A. Canfield collection by the New Jersey Historical Society (1930-1931); psychologist and collector Edward B. Titchener of Cornell University; and the Henry A. Ramsden Far Eastern collection, including a note to John Robinson about the terms of Ramsden’s will, a numbered list of Ramsden coins, and related materials, such as those pertaining to Far Eastern collector Giuseppe Ros, Italian consulate general in Shangai (R, 1913-1921). In addition to the correspondence are research materials, including notebooks on Indian Bull and Horseman series; files on Bryan Money, Mexican coins, Ethiopian (Abyssinian) coins, American medals (1918-1921), and Indian Peace Medals (1917); a handwritten index to the Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain and Ireland (1837-1911), The Indian Antiquary (1877-1919), and the Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bengal (1832-1910); and typed curator and committee reports (1913-1927).
  Howland Wood (1877-1938) was born in New Bedford, Massachusetts, and graduated from Brown University in 1900. He became a member of the ANS in 1909. By 1913 he had been appointed Curator, remaining in this position until his death in 1938. At that time, the Society only maintained a single curator, with two assistants. Despite the limited size of the staff, during Wood's tenure the Society's collections increased significantly, from 50,000 to almost 200,000 specimens. In addition to his curatorial duties, Wood also served as editor of the American Journal of Numismatics from 1910 to 1920. In 1920, Wood became only the third recipient of the Society's Archer M. Huntington Medal Award. Outside of the ANS, Wood also served as secretary to the American Numismatic Association from 1905 to 1909 and then as governor and chairman of the ANA's board from 1909 to 1912. After Wood's death, Edward T. Newell (ANS President, 1916-1941) eulogized Wood as "the ideal Curator," noting that "Howland Wood was one of those rare geniuses who combined an inherited urge to collect, an insatiable curiosity as to the 'why' and the 'wherefore,' and an orderly mind which could not brook obvious gaps or disorderly arrangement."
  See also Howland Wood personal correspondence, 1873, 1902-1938.